SHAYAK CHATTOPADHYAYA

OBJECTIVE

I am an Application Architect with over 19 years of experience in the fields of Development, Architecture, System Engineering, and Project Management.

PROFILE

I am an experienced Architect with a successful track record of delivering complex projects. As an Architect and System Engineer, I have developed distributed solutions and worked collaboratively with Network, Product, and Vendor teams. Additionally, I am a proven innovator with a patent, publication, and multiple Proofs of Concept under my belt.

Throughout my career, I have consistently managed projects and teams across geographies and have performed effectively under pressure. I have a proven ability to scale up teams through hiring, training, and mentoring. My experience spans across Architecture, System Design, System Engineering, Development, and Delivery Management.

My track record is characterized by delivering business benefits and cultivating long-term customer relationships.

SKILLS

Java | SIP | SDP | Azure | AWS | Cassandra | Networking
VoIP | Wireshark | SonarQube | Git | Project Management
Scrum | Linux | C++ | Mobicent | Websphere | ELK

PATENTS & PUBLICATIONS

- Inventor of **US Patent** # **11165836** to reduce VoIP call disruption
- Filed US Patent Application 17/305441 to prevent Telecom fraud.
- Publication in ip.com titled "Method and apparatus for selection of preferential based on response from SIP Redirect server"

EXPERIENCE

APPLICATION ARCHITECT, IBM

03/2015 - Till Date

Voice over IP Application Server, AT&T – This is a SIP signaling server managing sessions for VoIP calls for enterprise wireline market segments of AT&T like Retail, Wholesale, Transfer Connect

Responsibilities & Achievements

- Currently leading the effort to migrate SIP applications from Websphere to Mobicent for 400+ servers. This will help in developing highly scalable distributed solution.
- Designed & developed US 988 Suicide Helpline for AT&T Wireline business in AT&T
- Designed & developed STIR/SHAKEN functionality to identify spam calls working with Network & product teams, 3rd Party iConnectiv Registered Caller DB. This feature identifies caller identity using industry DB.
- Responsible for System Engineering, translating network design and technical specification into high level design
- Leading the development team with delivery ownership, ensuring quality control, code review, resolving production issues with large customers
- Static code analysis using Sonarqube across the cluster
- Mitigating application security vulnerabilities with SAST/DAST scan

DELIVERY MANAGER, IBM

03/2012 - 03/2015

Service Provisioning Platform, AT&T - The Service Provisioning Platform (SPP) is responsible for provisioning Layer 4 through Layer 7 features for all AT&T Voice and Enhanced services.

Responsibilities & Achievements

- Delivered LTE project with new GUI interface with a new team of front-end developers successfully against a challenging schedule.
- Introduced new code review practice in the team with a new code review template
- Went beyond customer SLA and effectively reduced number of static code defects YoY basis
- Effective in staffing, training, mentoring to speed up the delivery targets resulting in team expansion from 19 to 55 developers in 24 months
- People management with regular feedback sessions, yearly employee performance evaluation
- Maintained PM dashboards, Risks & issues, Delivery schedule

TEAM LEAD, IBM

07/2009 - 02/2012

Configuration Applications, AT&T – These set of applications are responsible for configuration and discovery of Layer 3 network elements

Responsibilities & Achievements

- Managing the scope of projects and tracking the daily progress.
- Creating Assembly Test Plan

SENIOR DEVELOPER, IBM

07/2007 - 06/2009

Network Topology Server, AT&T – These set of applications retrieve topology information from EMS/NMS and consolidate that information for processing in OSS

Responsibilities & Achievements

- Designed and developed a new interface with Alcatel-Lucent NMS
- Managed the PM dashboard and coordinated with the extended as the Application Project Manager

DEVELOPER, IBM

06/2004 - 06/2007

Network Configuration, AT&T – This application stores all the information related to Customer Premises Equipment of AT&T

Responsibilities & Achievements

- Developed the C++ code for migrating the application from DB2 to Oracle
- Implemented the corporate single sign-on feature for the application

VISA Have an approved US i140 and H1B Cap Exempt Visa

CERTIFICATIONS

- Microsoft Azure Fundamentals
- Certified Scrum Master (CSM)

EDUCATION

JADAVPUR UNIVERSITY, KOLKATA, M.TECH IN COMPUTER TECHNOLOGY

First Class

JADAVPUR UNIVERSITY, KOLKATA, B.E IN CONSTRUCTION ENGINEERING

First Class with Honors